Guide to the Namibia Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Namibia collection
1876-2005
MS 1534
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.75
(11 boxes)
The collection consists primarily of printed material relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Namibia. Some photographs are included.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of printed material relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Namibia. Some photographs are included.
Children -- Namibia; Education, Higher -- Namibia; Women -- Namibia; Namibia -- Description and travel; Namibia -- Geography; Namibia -- Politics and government; Namibia -- Social conditions; Namibia -- Economic conditions; Namibian literature; Photographs -- Namibia; SWAPO
- Inventory
  - Transcript of diary of W. C. Palgrave, Special Commissioner, appointed by the Imperial Government to act as liaison with native chiefs, 1876-1879 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Ethnographic studies, [1952?], 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Okavango Reconnaissance": maps and diagrams of the Okavango River, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Water Supply in Owamboland": maps, diagrams, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - South West Africa People's Organization (SWAPO): newsletters, bulletins, pamphlets, documents, 1962, 1970-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
  - Assorted writings on Namibia, various and unidentified sources, 1963, 1979, 1980-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Committee on Africa (ACOA) and the Africa Fund: newsletters, pamphlets, printed materials, 1967, 1981-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tourism: maps, brochures, 1973-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa (ECSA): newsletters, reports, 1973, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Convention of Namibia: constitutional proposals (announced by Clemens Kapuuo), 1976 March 9 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1976, 1982-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Namibia Review, A Journal of Contemporary South West African Affairs, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Namibia National Front (NNF): newsletters, manifestos, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - PROSWA/Namibia Foundation: news bulletins, activity reports, printed materials, 1978-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Afrikaans-Duitse Kultuurunie/Afrikaans-Deutsche Kulturgemeinschaft (ADK): booklets, reports, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Writings on SWAPO, unidentified, 1978, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - United Nations: newsletters, statements, press releases, lectures, 1978-1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Namibian Christian Democratic Party (NCDP): program and aim, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Namibia Support Committee: publications, 1979, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - SWAPO Democrats: releases and other documents, 1979-1980, 1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Democratic Turnhalle Alliance (DTA): manifestos, newsletters, pamphlets, 1979-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Anti-Apartheid Movement and other related organizations: printed materials, 1979-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Elections: printed material, pamphlets, registration forms, 1980, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Interessengemeinschaft Deutschsprachiger Südwester (IG); Organization of German Speaking Southwesters: newsletters, brochures, reports, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Campaign Against Namibian Uranium Contracts (CANUC) and materials from other anti-uranium movements, 1980-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Government of the United States: congressional records and other documents concerning Namibia, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - SWA/Namibia Information Service, Division Liaison Services, Department of Governmental Affairs: statements, publications, news briefs, 1980-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 29 - 30)
  - Newspapers, 1980-1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Meeting on South West Africa/Namibia in Geneva," Department of Foreign Affairs and Information: information newsletter, 1981 January 7-14 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Education/academic journals, 1981, [1987?]-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Labour Party: Statement by the National Executive Committee, 1981 April (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Rössing Uranium Limited: newsletters, magazines, 1981, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - International Defense and Aid Fund for Southern Africa (IDAF): briefings, pamphlets, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Human rights organizations: reports, printed materials, [1981?]-[1984?] (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Washington Office on Africa: newsletters, releases, publications, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Der Deutsch-Südafrikaner: newsletter, 1982 Jan/February (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - The Seventh Annual African Feast, The Black Vanguard Resource Center (BVRC): newsletter, 1982 April 16-17 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - SWAPO Youth League: bulletins and pamphlets, 1982, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - International Conference in Solidarity with the Struggle of the People of Namibia (and related material), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - The Rio Tinto-Zinc Corporation: "The Alternative Report", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Swedish organizations: reports, printed materials, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Namibia Support Committee: newsletters, reports, pamphlets, 1983-1989 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Worker/labor organizations: pamphlets, booklets, publications, printed materials, 1983-1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - The American Society for the Defence of Tradition, Family, Property (TFP): position papers on SWAPO, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - "Namibian Independence: What is the Goal and How Can We Achieve It?," by Jariretundu Kozonguizi, Lincoln Review, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Amnesty International: pamphlets, bulletins, letters, 1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Feminist organizations: pamphlets, releases, literary journals, 1985-1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Nangoloh, Phil Ya, articles by and about, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Namibia Communications Center: interviews, reports, 1986-1991 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - "Children - Apartheid and Repression in Namibia," South Africa the Imprisoned Society (SATIS): seminar packet, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - South West Africa National Union (SWANU): newsletters, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Tenth anniversary of Cassinga Day, memorial services, [1988] (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - "The First Crisis of the Implementation of UNSCR 435/78 in Namibia," Radio Mozambique, External Service, Studio Discussion, 1989 April 9 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Office of the Administrator General: press release, 1989 November 14 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Literary journals, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Namibia Peace Plan Study and Contact Group (NPP 435): press releases, pamphlets, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Southern Africa Dossier, Centro de Estudos Africanos Universidade Eduardo Mondlane - Maputo República Popular de Moçambique: reports, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - International Freedom Foundation (UK), 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Namibia Communications Centre: reports, printed materials, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Namibia National Students' Organisation (NANSO): resolutions, newspapers, 1989-1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - National Conference on Land Reform and the Land Question: Consensus Document, 1991 July (Box 4, Folder 63A)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsbriefs, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - "Business Opportunities in SWA/Namibia," published by First National Development Corporation of SWA Ltd., undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - The Federal Party of South West Africa: constitution, aims, undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Namibia Democratic Coalition: printed materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Namibian National Democratic Party: election manifesto, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Republikeinse Party: manifestos, printed materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - United Democratic Front (UDF): election manifesto, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Owamba: photographs and brochures, [pre 1910?], [1981?] (Box 4, Folder 71)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-196
  - Additional printed materials, 1970-1998, undated (Box 1)
  - Additional printed materials, 1970-1998, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1906-1913, undated (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-029
  General note
  Also includes Accession 2000-M-143
  - Additional printed materials, 1952-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Photographs, 1893-1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Report on the Natives of South-West Africa and Their Treatment by Germany," [prepared by the Administrator's Office, Windhuk, South-West Africa; photocopy], 1918 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Statements of the Natives of South-West Africa as to Their Future and the Future Government of the Country," [enclosure no.7, photocopy], 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-031
  - AIDS Law Unit, Legal Assistance Center, "Your Guide on How to Write a Valid Will", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Citizen N- Corruption Isn't Worth It!", 2003 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Desert Research Foundation of Namibia, 2000 February (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "435 Watch," no. 9, 1989 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Gobabeb Training and Research Center", 1999 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Labour Resource and Research Institute (LaRRI), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Namibia Institute for Democracy (NID), "Democracy, the Role We Play", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Namibia National Front News" (NNF), no. 20, 1980 February (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Namibia News Gazette, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1981 Jul, 1981 July (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Namibian HIV/AIDS Charter of Rights" and other HIV/AIDS related materials, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Namibian National Symbols", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Namibian Woman, National Women's Day, 29 Years of Heroic Struggle," Vol 5, [1988] December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Namibia's National Programme to Combat Desertification" (NAPCOD), 1997 May, [1999] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Union of Namibian Workers (NUNW), "Affirmative Action for Trade Unions", 1998 November (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - News Bulletin, nos. 1, 2, 3, 1979 Oct, 1980 Mar, November (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Take a Stand and Vote", [1999] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Times of Namibia, vol. 1, no. 12, 1991 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The Voice of SWAPO-D," nos. 3, 4, 1979 May 10, 1979 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Water Point Management of the Four 'O' Regions" (Ohangwena, Omusati, Oshikoto, Oshana), 2000 March (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photograph [Namibian women], possible photographer, John Liebenberg, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Additional Material, 1940-1999; Accession 2010-M-112
  - "Die Finse Sending in Ovamboland," by W. Nicol, Visie-President en Voorsitter Finansies Komitee, Die Christenraad van Suid-Afrika (one page), 1940 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New Partnership for Africa's Development (NEPAD), series of eleven briefings, Circa 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - UNIN News: bimonthly publication of the United Nations Institute for Namibia, 1978 Nov, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, Mid 1900s-2000s; Accession 2015-M-001; 2.5
  - Printed material, Circa 1970-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - The Seven Plagues of Africa: Volume 2, The People Oppressed, Mid 1900s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Posters, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 1)